Super hot summer.... Mango
sorbet.... Ninja creamy let's go!
Now before we go too far into this ice cream
video, for the first time on this channel I want
to ask something of you, all of you watching if
you're an animal lover this might hit home. Very
good friends of ours have a dog called Maisie,
she's only 2 years old. She has unfortunately
got problems with her back legs which means she
really struggles to walk, at only 2 years old
you can understand that there's a lot of life left
for her but the operations she needs are going to
cost $10,000 Canadian dollar. Now our friends are
a single earning family, one of them is at school
fulltime and the other one works for an airline.
I'm asking you personally if you can help out,
please head over to their GoFundMe page
and offer any support that you can.
I've donated from the business, my wife has
also donated individually. Even if it's $1,
every dollar will help get Maisie the
care she needs to have a better life
thanks for listening to this pledge
and let's get on with the ice cream.
So our neighbors gave us some mangos the other
day, they're really really ripe and they're right
at the edge of their lifespan so we're going to
make a delicious mango sorbet, it's super simple
you can actually use this recipe in any ice cream
machine that you have so let's get on with it.
So sorbet balance is actually surprisingly simple
because it's much higher water, there's no cream,
there's a lot of sugar in sorbet but that sugar is
needed to stop it turning into a block of ice. For
those that have followed along on the channel, I
like to help with the science of ice cream making
so you understand why we use the ingredients
that we do and what they do in your recipes.
So sugar affects the freezing point of
any ice cream, gelato, sherbet, sorbet,
any thing like that. The sugar will affect
the freezing point and that stops and slows
down the progression of Ice Crystal formation
as it freezes so it will keep doing that until
you add so much sugar, that it won't freeze
at all. Salt does the same thing and that is
why you can go to some of the coldest places on
Earth and still see liquid water flowing at you
know -10°C it's so highly salinated that
it just can't freeze at that temperature.
If you ever put an ice cream mix in
your machine and it just doesn't freeze,
then you've got too much sugar and or other
things that change the freezing point.
Anyway let's chitter chatter, let's
prepare our mango. Super simple,
we're going to use a cold process stabilizer,
guar gum, so we don't even have to heat this
up. We're going to put it all in a blender
and then get it in our ninja creamy tubs.
What I'm going to do is I'm going to split
this mix up I'm going to put some in the
creamy tub....... I'm going to sneeze "5
minutes later" I'm going to put some in
the creamy tub and some I will keep aside and
I will put in my ice cream machine my muso.
So it really is super super simple to make
sorbet, what people generally do with sorbet
is over complicate it and and try and do
some really random kind of stuff you know,
and that's fine if you understand
how ice cream and whatever else works
so let's
let's get ....right these are super soft blimy,
right, old school we're looking
here for 314g of mango flesh.
Those mangoes were like the sloppiest mangoes
I've ever worked with so let's get those out
the way and man I need to tidy up before we go
any further....... That's better, I'm not all
sticky sorbet now. Right so we've got
our 314g three 314g of mango in there,
we're now going to add on top 420g of water,
cold water straight out the tap is fine...
There and straight onto that we're going
to add 210g of sugar. We're going to add
200g in here first 5 points for anyone that
can tell me why I'm keeping 10g back.....
Yes it's because I need to mix
the stabilizer in with that
sugar. If you're new to the channel any
stabilizer needs a....... hold on......
Any stabilizer needs to be mixed
with a sugar or a powdered solid
of some kind so milk powder you know,
um cocoa powder, anything like that.
It's 3.5g of guar gum going in this
remaining 10g of sugar. Because if
you don't mix the stabilizer with some
of the sugar, it will clump up and then
you'll not actually use a lot of it
it will just clump up and do nothing.
So with the stabilizer mixed in with your
sugar just swirl it around use a spoon use a
fork use a mini whisk whatever and all those
lumps of go have now broken up and they are
ultra fine ready to go in here. One final
ingredient to go in here and that is.....
Corn syrup.... corn syrup, glucose syrup,
golden syrup, you could even use dextrose
if you wanted to it doesn't matter. We're
just changing the freezing point here,
this brings the.... this, just this ingredient
will change the serving temperature from -10°C
to -16°C that means that.......
52g of this by the way
That means that you don't have to
sit there for 95 years waiting,
here we go, waiting for your ice
cream to soften up to eat it you
can just eat it. Anyway stabilizer in
that's it what we're going to do now
is put this on the right
way and we are going to blend this for about
30 seconds or something like that so I'll
do that and then I'll have a quick tidy up
and we'll come back.... low speed is fine!
That is it, no super complicated this that
and the other, Ultra smooth liquid like that
we have. How this works is the frictional heat in
the blender aids the creation of a sugar syrup,
the water and the sugar combined, then
mix with the stabilizer, in this case
the guar gum. The Guar gum stabilizes that
water, makes it thicker and more viscous,
combined with the mango which has sugar and water
in it as well, we get this Ultra smooth liquid so
that is now going to go into the freezer like
this and before anyone says the purest mango
sorbet is just mangos...... that is not sorbet!
Anyway I'm going to put the rest of this in the
container I'll sling that in the fridge and
use that in a another video probably, but
I'll come back when that is completely Frozen and
we'll dish some up and show you what it's like.
Got the other half of this churning
here that's nearly finished so let's
get the ninja one in......
it is plugged in.....
So as this one's finished as well, let's dish
them both up let's compare mango sorbet. This
recipe has been designed to work in the Ninja
creamy and in your traditional ice cream machine.
So creamy there I need something to put
this ice cream in. Okay let's get some
dished up in this bowl we have the ninja
and in this bowl we we have the churned
version so from the close-up you can see there's
a slight difference in color the ninja one is
a little bit lighter in color the churned
one one is a little bit darker and that is
"interesting" super refreshing great texture
on that churned one now this one looks better
well so sorbet the ninja one wins out
why does it win out well it's obviously
put the right amount of movement into
the sbet IT sheared the ice crystals
into a nice small size it's done a better
job at that than the muo traditional ice
cream machine both flavors are impeccable
now the color is indicative of the amount
of shearing that happens not necessarily air
um a good sbet recipe needs a little bit of
air but actually what you're doing is you're
just you're breaking the ice crystals up into
a smaller size you're not really interested in
overrun per se you will get some especially in
a churn machine you you won't get that in the
creamy but you obviously get a much stronger
Shear in the creamy and that creates actually
a smoother sorbet so that's really interesting
flavor-wise they're basically identical but
this one being a bit denser it is super smooth
super
smooth you would not be able to tell that that
is sorbet 100% you would not tell that sorbet,
that that's basically mango ice cream
so sorbet the science behind sorbet is
different to ice cream, different to gelato,
it needs the higher sugar but what you've got
here is a really simple recipe for probably
one of the best sorbet you're going to try.
Don't just throw fruit in your Ninja creamy
and hope it turns out well it just won't,
it won't turn out nice it this balanced
sorbet recipe is exquisite, try it.
Will it work with other fruit .....um to a degree
yes but this recipe is balanced just for mango,
every fruit has a different amount
of sugar, different amount of water,
you start playing with those you adjust the
recipe and you'll take it out of that balance
bubble that we need it to be
in. Every fruit is different,
there is no "one recipe fits all" unfortunately
for the world of ice cream, gelato and sorbet,
but delicious mango sorbet..... the ninja creami
wins out over the musso churning machine which is
interesting thanks very much for watching,
don't forget to like and subscribe
and I'll see you next week 👍